Congregational Library & Archives Artwork collection, 1770-1998, undated.
Congregational Library & Archives
Congregational Library & Archives Artwork collection, 1770-1998, undated.
RG5459
Congregational Library & Archives
51 Items
This collection was formed in 2023 as a way to quickly see all of the artwork that is in the Congregational Library & Archives. The list will likely see growth as we identify pieces of artwork located elsewhere in the collection or with the purchase of new pieces. This collections contains 51 pieces of artwork. A majoirty of the 51 pieces are portraits, but the collection also includes architectural drawings and a bust.
Restrictions on Access
For both preservation and display purposes, many of the pieces of artwork have been framed. Framed pieces at the CLA will not be removed from their frames without the express permission of the Executive Director.
Acquisition Information
The items within this collection have accumulated over the history of the organization and many lack clear acquisition information. When their is information on the source of acquisition, it will be noted under the individual item. An example of this can be seen with the Nancy E. Forsberg portrait.
Historical Note
This collection was formed in 2023 as a way to quickly see all of the artwork that is in the Congregational Library & Archives. The list will likely see growth as we identify pieces of artwork located elsewhere in the collection or with the purchase of new pieces.
Scope and Contents
This collections contains 51 pieces of artwork. A majoirty of the 51 pieces are portraits, but the collection also includes architectural drawings and a bust.
Arrangement
The collection is arragned by physical location and includes 12 series and 3 sub-series.
Arrangement of the Collection
Series 1:
Reading Room, 1770, undated
Series 2:
Archives Office, 1770, 1866, undated
Series 3:
Rare Book Room Flat Files, 1857, 1901, undated
Subseries 1:
Drawer 9, 1901, undated
Subseries 2:
Drawer 18, 1857, undated
Series 4:
First Floor Stacks Flat Files, 1865, 1869, 1998, undated
Subseries 1:
Drawer 13, 1865, 1869, 1998, undated
Series 5:
Assistant Librarian's Office, 1875, undated
Series 6:
Hitchcock Room, 1898, 1901, undated
Series 7:
Director of Development Office, 1900
Series 8:
Office Side Hallway, 1922, undated
Series 9:
Boates Conference Room, undated
Series 10:
Development Office, undated
Series 11:
Executive Director's Office, undated
Series 12:
Librarian's Office, undated
Portraits.; Women Clergy.; Clergy -- Pictorial works.; Busts.; Architecture -- Designs and plans
- Reading Room, 1770, undated; 5 Items
  - Lyman Beecher, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 41 x 51 in (Object 1)
  - George Whitefield, 1770; Blyth, Benjamin; 1 Item Oil painting 40 x 36 in (Object 2)
  - Samuel Hopkins, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 25 x 30 in (Object 3)
  - Jonathan Mayhew, undated; Greenwood, John; 1 Item Oil painting 30 x 25 in (Object 4)
  - Nathaniel Emmons, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 27 x 30 in (Object 5)
- Archives Office, 1770, 1866, undated; 4 Items
  - Isaac P. Langworthy, undated; 1 Item Charcoal portrait 31 x 35 in (Object 1)
  - Pilgrim Society Certificate of Thomas M. Boss, 1866; 1 Item Engraving 21 x 26.5 in (Object 2)
  - Congregational House, undated; 1 Item Photograph 14.5 x 17.5 in (Object 3)
  - Old South Church (Boston Third), 1770; 1 Item Sketch 23.5 x 20 in (Object 4)
    Biographical / Historical
    This is the only signed architectural rendering by Thomas Dawes, a prominent Boston architect of the eigteenth century. It shows a set of commercial buildings, to be erected on the corner of Marlborough (now Washington) and Milk Streets. Dawes later gained fame as a patriot during the Revolutionary War. One of the Old South papers, on permanent loan to the Congregational Library.
- Rare Book Room Flat Files, 1857, 1901, undated; 11 Items
  - Drawer 9, 1901, undated; 2 Items
    - Nathaniel Taylor Bust, undated; Tyler, Amelia; 1 Item Sculpture 13 x 16.5 x 3 in (Folder 1)
    - Cottonus Matherus, 1901; 1 Item Lithograph 41 x 40 cm (Folder 2)
      Historical Note
      This is a reproduction of the work by Peter Pelham.
  - Drawer 18, 1857, undated; 9 Items
    - John Moorhead, undated; 1 Item Photograph 15.5 x 11.5 in (Folder 3)
    - William Hooper, undated; 1 Item Photograph 15.5 x 11.5 in (Folder 4)
    - Chauncy Hall School & First Congregational Church Boston, 1857; 1 Item Hand-colored lithograph 17 x 21 in (Folder 5)
    - Edwards A. Park, undated; 1 Item Photograph 15 x 20 in (Folder 6)
    - Austin Phelps, undated; 1 Item Lithograph 13 x 16 in (Folder 7)
    - Congregational Library Bookplate, undated; 1 Item Photograph 22.5 x 15.5 in (Folder 8)
    - The First Reformers at the Diet of Spires in 1529, undated; Sartain and Doty; 1 Item Engraving 28.5 x 33 (Folder 9)
    - International Congregational Council in London (with partial list of members), undated; A & B Taylor; 1 Item Photograph 29 x 15 (Folder 10)
    - Jotham Sewall, undated; 1 Item Charcoal 22 x 20 in. (Folder 11)
- First Floor Stacks Flat Files, 1865 1998; 1865, 1869, 1998, undated; 8 Items
  - Drawer 13, 1865 1998; 1865, 1869, 1998, undated; 8 Items
    - S. Brainard Pratt, undated; 1 Item Photograph 24 x 18 in (Folder 12)
    - Photo of CLA at Somerset Street (1 of 2), undated; 1 Item Photograph 24 x 19 in (Folder 13)
    - Photo of CLA at Somerset Street (2 of 2), undated; 1 Item Photograph 24 x 19 in (Folder 14)
    - National Congregational Council at Plymouth Rock, June 22, 1865; Whipple, John Adams, 1822-1891; 1 Item Photograph 14.5 x 18 (Folder 15)
    - Landing of the Pilgrims on Plymouth Rock, 1620, 1869; 1 Item Engraving 18 x 24 in (Folder 16)
    - International Congregational Council in London (without partial list of members), undated; A & B Taylor; 1 Item Photograph 29 x 15" (Folder 17)
    - Photo of bas-relief from building: Religious Faith, undated; 1 Item Photograph 25 x 30.5 (Folder 18)
    - Photo of bas-relief from building: Philanthropy, undated; 1 Item Photograph 25 x 30.5 (Folder 19)
    - Nancy E. Forsberg portrait, 1998; Unknown; 1 Item (Folder 20)
      Restrictions on Access
      For both preservation and display purposes, many of the pieces of artwork have been framed. Framed pieces at the CLA will not be removed from their frames without the express permission of the Executive Director.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by Mary Lou Mayfield in August, 2020; accession 2020-09. Originally assigned identification number MS5414 before it was merged into this collection.
      Nancy E. Forsberg was born on August 5, 1922 in Jersey City and moved to Maplewood, New Jersey in 1926. She graduated Phi Beta Kappa from Denison University and worked as an educator in Ohio and worked at the YWCA In Connecticut. She graduated from Yale University School of Divinity in 1951 and was ordained the same year; she was one of only three women who graduated from the divinity school that year. She later graduated with a masters in education from New York University. She returned to Maplewood and became pastor of the First Congregational Church in Union, New Jersey, in 1967. While serving as pastor, Rev. Nancy became a leader in interfaith and interracial efforts; she is credited with helping to bring Holocaust studies into Union-area schools. She also led an interfaith Bus Ministry which brought groups of people on spiritually focused trips across the United States, Canada, Europe, and Israel. She served as the pastor of the First Congregational Church, now the Faith United Church of Christ, until her retirement in 2000. She died on April 5, 2008.
      Scope and Contents
      This collection contains a single portrait of Nancy E. Forsburg. The portrait was created by an unknow artist in 1998. Portrait is, likely, charcoal on paper.
      Faith United Church of Christ (Union (Union County, N.J.)); Forsberg, Nancy E.; Forsberg, Nancy E. -- Portraits.
- Assistant Librarian's Office, 1875, undated; 5 Items
  - A.J.F. Behrends, undated; 1 Item Lithograph 27.5 x 32 in (Object 1)
  - William Jenks, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 35 x 43 in (Object 2)
  - Enoch Pond, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 34 x 39 in (Object 3)
  - Alonzo H. Quint, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 37 x 42 in (Object 4)
  - Samuel Johnson, 1875; 1 Item Oil painting 40 x 45 in (Object 5)
- Hitchcock Room, 1898, 1901, undated; 4 Items
  - Nathaniel G. Clark, 1898; 1 Item Oil painting 34.5 x 38.5 in (Object 1)
  - Cotton Mather, 1901; 1 Item Lithograph 15.5 x 19.5 in (Object 2)
  - Joseph S. Clark, undated; Clark, Joseph S.; 1 Item Oil painting 25 x 30 in (Object 3)
  - Samuel A. Hitchcock, undated; Willard, William; 1 Item Oil painting 25 x 30 in (Object 4)
- Director of Development Office, 1900; 1 Item
  - Henry Martin Dexter, 1900; 1 Item Oil painting 36 x 41 in (Object 1)
- Office Side Hallway, 1922, undated; 5 Items
  - Henry Ward Beecher, undated; Hall, George R.; 1 Item Lithograph 29 x 35.75 in (Object 1)
  - Horace Bushnell, undated; 1 Item Charcoal drawing 26 x 32 in (Object 2)
  - William H. Cobb, 1922; 1 Item Oil painting 32 x 37 in (Object 3)
  - Frederick W. Robertson, undated; 1 Item Charcoal drawing 31 x 37 in (Object 4)
  - Rufus Anderson, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 32 x 39 in (Object 5)
- Boates Conference Room, undated; 1 Item
  - Jacob Ide, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 29.5 x 35 in (Object 1)
- Development Office, undated; 2 Items
  - Augustus Thompson, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 33.5 x 40 in (Object 1)
  - Samuel B. Capen, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 30.5 x 35 in (Object 2)
- Executive Director's Office, undated; 4 Items
  - Edward Kirk, undated; 1 Item Oil painting 40 x 47.5 in (Object 1)
  - Charles G. Finney, undated; 1 Item Photograph (copy) 17.25 x 20.25 in (Object 2)
  - Bas-relief from 14 Beacon Street: Law, undated; 1 Item Photograph 30.5 x 26.5 in (Object 3)
  - Bas-relief from 14 Beacon Street: Religion, undated; 1 Item Photograph 30.5 x 26.5 in (Object 4)
- Librarian's Office, undated; 1 Item
  - Biblearium sign, undated; 1 Item Framed sign 7 x 22 in (Object 1)